M. Katy Rodriguez Wimberly

NSF MPS Ascend Postdoctoral Fellow · University of California, Riverside

■ mwimb002@ucr.edu | ★ mkrodriguezwimberly.github.io | ★ @astronomouse | ORCID: 0000-0003-1848-5571

Research Statement(s)_

I study Near–Field Cosmology and Galaxy Evolution using both optical telescopes and cosmological simulations. In particular, my work focuses on ultra-faint dwarf galaxies — researching these possible relics of the first galaxies ever formed to learn more about the Early Universe, how the earliest galaxies evolve, and how they can be used as a tool to learn more about our own galaxy, the Milky Way.

Alongside this astrophysics research, I work to improve the astronomical community for all, including publishing articles to help spread successful programs. I have created peer mentorship programs implemented at my alma mater, UC Irvine, wand within the Cal-Bridge Program. My aim is to normalize a holistic approach to academic success and strengthen marginalized communities.

Education

University of California, Irvine

Irvine, California

Ph.D. in Physics

Sep 2016 - Dec 2021

- · Thesis Advisor: Prof. Michael Cooper
- Thesis: Ultra-Faint Dwarf Galaxies: Investigating the Evolution of Our Universe & Those Who Study It

University of California, Irvine

Irvine, California

M.S. in Physics

Sep 2016 - June 2019

Aug 2015 - May 2016

• GPA: 3.34 out of possible 4.00

California State University, Long Beach

California State University, Long Beach

Long Beach, California

M.S. in Physics

- GPA: 4.00 out of possible 4.00
- Transferred to Ph.D. Program

Long Beach, California

Jan 2011 - May 2015

B.S. in Physics

- · Minor: Math
- Overall GPA: 3.15 out of possible 4.00
- Major GPA: 3.20 out of possible 4.00

Mount San Antonio College

Walnut, California

ΑА

Jan 2004 - June 2009

- Majors: Fine Arts, Natural Science & Math, Social & Behavioral Sciences
- Overall GPA: 3.32 out of possible 4.00

Publications

A Model of Mentorship for Students from Historically Underrepresented Groups in STEM Rodriguez Wimberly, M.K., et al.

Understanding Interventions

- · Under Review
- arXiv: 2209.03395

Sizing from the Smallest Scales: The Mass of the Milky Way

MNRAS, 513, 4968

Rodriguez Wimberly, M.K., et al.

Characterizing the Infall Times and Quenching Timescales of the Milky Way Satellites with Gaia Proper Motions

MNRAS

Fillingham, S.P. et al.

2019

- · Under Review
- arXiv: 1906..04180

Suppressing Star Formation on the Smallest Scales: What Role Does Environment Play? Rodriguez Wimberly, M.K., et al.

MNRAS, 483, 4031

2019

SETI Observations of Exoplanets with the Allen Telescope Array

AJ, 152.6 (2016b): 181

Harp, G.R. et al.

2016

RODRIGUEZ WIMBERLY CV DECEMBER 20, 2022 1/7

Highlighted Awards

NSF MPS Ascend Postdoctoral Fellow, 2021 - Current AAS National Osterbrock Fellow, 2020 - 2021 NSF Graduate Research Fellow, 2016 - 2021 Eugene Cota-Robles Fellow, 2016 - 2021

Teaching Experience _____

ASTR110L: Introduction to Astronomy Lab

CSU Long Beach

Instructor on Record

Aug 2015 - May 2016

- Duties included creating and implementing syllabi based off the department's experiment schedule, homework assignments, exams and final projects (sample syllabi can be viewed at https://mkrodriguezwimberly.github.io/outreach_teaching_service/astro100Lsyllabus.html).
- CSULB Official Instructor Evaluations were given after each term and I was guided on how to interpret the feedback and implement desired improvements by the CSULB Physics & Astronomy Department Chair.

Highlighted Mentorship _____

Cal-Bridge Mentorship Handbook

Revision Team Lead June 2021

- Led team of 4 other Cal-Bridge Alumni in rewriting the program's mentorship handbook with the guidance of the program's director.
- Revisions focus on reciprocal mentor-mentee relationships (especially in that as much as students need to adapt to academia, mentors and academia need to adapt to students), highlighting hurdles specific to many underrepresented groups within STEM, and mental health
- Publicly available at https://tinyurl.com/CBMentorshipHandbook

Cal-Bridge Mentor Map

Author Aug 2020

- Created a Mentor/Support Network Map designed specifically for undergraduate STEM students.
- Publicly available at https://tinyurl.com/CBMentorshipMap

Observing Experience _____

2 Nights Keck Observatory , Scheduled for May 2023, Mass-Metallicity Relation for UFDs	LRIS, Lead Co-I
1.5 Nights Keck Observatory , Chemical Abundances in UFD, Willman 1	DEIMOS, Lead Co-I
15 Nights Keck Observatory , Extragalactic Star Formation Quenching Survey	DEIMOS, Co-I
Oct 2015 UCO/Lick Observatory, Robert P. Kraft Observational Astronomy Workshop	

Skills

Programming	Python (Pandas, SciPy, NumPy, Scikit-learn, AstroPy), IRAF (DEIMOS Mask Design, Wavelength Calibration), MySQL, Fortran95,
Programming	Mathematica, HTML, Certified LabVIEW Associate Developer
Tools	Unix, Shell (Bash/Zsh), ŁTĘX(Overleaf/R Markdown), Pypelt, Aladin, DS9, Gwyddion, Git, Atomic & Magnetic Force Microscopy.
Soft Skills	Time Management, Teamwork, Problem-solving, Documentation, Engaging Presentation.

Society Memberships _____

Astronomical Society of the Pacific, Board of Directors Member, Diversity Committee Co-Chair	2017 - Present
American Astronomical Society, Member, Early Career Task Force Member	2015 - Present
American Physical Society, Member	2015 - 2017
Society of Physics Students - CSULB, CSULB Chapter Secretary (2013-2015), Member	2011 - 2015

Invited Talks

Astronomy Colloquium, University of Texas, Austin, Department of Astronomy	upcoming Apr'23
First Friday Astronomy, Boise State University, Department of Physics	upcoming Mar'23
241 st Meeting of the American Astronomical Society , NSF AAPF Symposium Mentorship Panelist	upcoming Jan'23
Astronomy Colloquium, University of Michigan, Department of Astronomy	September 2022
Conversations in Equity & Inclusion, University of Michigan, Department of Astronomy	September 2022
Astronomy Brown Bag Lunch, MIT	May 2022
Physics & Astronomy Colloquium, Pomona College	April 2022
Cosmology & Astronomy Seminar, University of California, Davis	October 2021
Cosmology & Astronomy Seminar, University of California, Davis	October 2021
CCAPP Little Galaxies Meeting, The Ohio State University	October 2021
Lunchtime Seminar, The Carnegie Observatories	September 2021
Lunchtime Seminar, The Carnegie Observatories	February 2020
Barriers to Equity, Inclusion & Diversity in Astronomy , Plenary Speaker, Presented on Imposter Syndrome, Astronomical Society of the Pacific 130^{th} Annual Meeting	September 2018
Syndrome, Astronomical society of the Facine 150 Annual Meeting	

Recent Contributed Presentations

241 st Meeting of the American Astronomical Society , NSF AAPF Symposium Contributed Oral	uncomina lan'22	
Presentation and Lightening Talk	upcoming Jan'23	
Astronomical Society of the Pacific 2022: A Virtual Conference, Contributed Oral Presentation	December 2022	
Keck Science Meeting, Oral Presentation	September 2022	
GalFESCA Conference, Oral Presentation	September 2022	
${f 240}^{th}$ Meeting of the American Astronomical Society, Dissertation Contributed Oral Presentation	June 2022	
Science by Diverse Scientists: A Cal-Bridge Physics & Astronomy Seminar, Oral Presentation	April 2022	
Galaxy Formation & Evolution in the Era of the Roman Space Telescope, Oral Presentation	October 2020	
Space Telescope Science Institute's 2020 Spring Symposium — The Local Group: Assembly &	September 2020	
Evolution , Poster Presentation	September 2020	

Highlighted Service Activities

American Astronomical Society Early Career Task Force

Invited Early Career Task Force Member

Cal-Bridge Mentorship Committee Chair

Cal-Bridge Program: A bridge program assisting undergraduate STEM students into graduate programs • Led revision of program's mentorship handbook

· Led creation and execution of professional development workshop focused on relational mentoring using the revised mentorship handbook

Astronomical Society of the Pacific Board of Directors Member

Diversity Committee Co-Chair & Jr. Board Fellow Selection Committee Co-Chair

Cal-Bridge Director of Peer Mentoring Program

Creator & Organizer of Peer Mentoring Program for Cal-Bridge Scholars

APS-IDEA Network: UCI Team Member

Network creating equitable, inclusive and diverse communities

UCI Physics & Astronomy Community Excellence

- Co-Creator of Peer Mentoring Programs for 1st Year Physics Graduate Students
- Group Sessions & 1-on-1 Mentoring with Trained Peer Mentors
- Our Website: uci-pace.github.io

2022 - Present

2020 - Present

2019 - Present

2019 - Present

2018-2021

2020-2021

Highlighted Media Pieces.

Mercury Magazine Contributor (Research Focus)

Astronomical Society of the Pacific

2018 - Present

Author: Katy Rodriguez Wimberly

Road to Happiness: Featured Alumni Story

California Sate University STEM Network

Author: Monica Alarcon

August 2022

The Reionization of Katy Rodriguez Wimberly

UC Irvine School of Physical Sciences Features

September 2021 Author: Lucas Van Wyk Joel

Ultra-Faint Dwarf Galaxies: Cosmic Fossils?

2018-2020

AstronoMouse YouTube SciComm Playlist

Creator: Katy Rodriguez Wimberly

Speaker: Katy Rodriguez Wimberly

Katy Rodriguez Wimberly: Changing My Life for Science

The Story Collider: True, Personal Stories About Science

May 2017

Employment History

UCI Competitive Edge Program, Graduate Student Peer Mentor	2017 & 2018
UCI Competitive Edge Program, Graduate Student Researcher	2016
CSLUB Physics Dept., Teaching Assistant - Astronomy Lab Instructor	2015-2016
UCI Summer Internship Program, Cal-Bridge Student Researcher	2015
US Army Reserves , Staff Sergeant, Saxophonist, Human Resources Manager	2003-2015
CSLUB Physics Dept., Learning Assistant	2013-2015
SETI Institute REU, CAMPARE Student Researcher	2014
LSAMP Academic Year Fellowship, Student Researcher	2013-2014
University of Texas, Brownsville Physics REU, Student Researcher	2012
CSULB Physics Dept., Winter Research Student Researcher	2012
Dept. of Defense Army Civilian , 300th Army Band Unit Administrator	2009-2012
Anbeten Productions, Design Assistant/Consultant	2006-2009
Disneyland Attractions Dept. , Innoventions Supervisor, Project Lead & Performer	2007-2009
Mt. San Antonio College Theatre Dept., Asst. Costumer	2006
Disneyland Entertainment Dept. , Costumer & Atmosphere Character	2003-2006

References _____

Dr. Laura SalesProfessor - UC Riverside

lsales@ucr.edu - 951.827.7037

Dr. Michael CooperProfessor - UC Irvine

cooper@uci.edu - 949.824.6485

Dr. Alex JiProfessor - University of Chicago

alexji@uchicago.edu - 773.702.8203

Dr. Alex RudolphProfessor - Cal Poly Pomona

alrudolph@cpp.edu - 909.717.1851

Previous Awards

UCI Latino Excellence & Achievement Award, 2020

UCI Physics & Astronomy Department Award for Outstanding Contributions, 2019

UCI Graduate Division Tom Angell Mentor Fellowship, 2019

Doctoral Diversity Initiative Fellow, 2016

Diversity Recruitment Fellowship, 2016

Nevin Graduate Endowment Fellowship, 2016

CSU-UC Cal-Bridge Scholar, 2014 - 2017

LSAMP PROUD Scholar Award, 2015

CSULB Physical Sciences and Mathematics Scholar , 2014

CSULB Physics Department Scholarship, 2014

Louis Stokes' Alliance for Minority Participation Academic Year Fellow, 2013 - 2014

CSULB Physics Department Scholarship, 2013

Past Service Activities

DreamWakers Speaker 2017 - Present

Virtual chats with grade school science classrooms.

NASA SMD Bridge Program Workshop

2022

Early Career Prospectives Breakout Discussion Facilitator.

EmpowHER: Empowering Women through High School Engagement and STEM Research-Keynote Speaker

2022

Inaugural Annual Conference to enhance student success in STEM

University of California, Irvine

UCI Competitive Edge Workshop Leader

2020

Created and Lead Workshop on Impostor Phenomena

APS Conference for Undergraduate Women in Physics at UCI

2020

Local Organizing Committee

UCI Astronomy Outreach

- Assisted in proposal, promotion, recruitment, and programming
- Co-Leader of ASCEND@UCI Mini Conference Our Website: https://sites.uci.edu/cuwip2020/ascend-at-uci/

Astronomical Society of the Pacific Junior Board Fellow

2017-2019

First ever Junior Board Fellow on the ASP Board of Directors

Bruin Brains Research Conference - Keynote Speaker

2019

TRIO Programming at Salt Lake Community College, UT

Expand Your Horizons Event - Keynote Speaker

2019

Annual Workshop for 6-10th Grade Girls Interested in STEM

Salt Lake Community College, UT

UCI Physics & Astronomy Inclusive Excellence Committee

2017-2019

Department Committee to Improve Climate and Diversity

A Graduate Student Representative

UCI Physics & Astronomy Physics Graduate Caucus

2017-2019 Mentorship Chair

Department Organization to Improve Graduates' Experience

UCI Physics & Astronomy Admission Task Force

2018-2019

A Graduate Student Representative

Department Committee to Improve Diversity in Admissions

2016-2019

Telescope Volunteer for Elementary-level Classroom Night Sky Viewing Parties

Astronomy Outreach for Underrepresented Youth

2016-2019

K-12 Classroom Visits for underrepresented groups ranging from ethnic minorities to Autistic and Downs Syndrome students.

Letters to a Pre-Scientist Scientist Pen Pal Pen Pal during each Academic Year with a grade school student interested in space science.	2015-2019
UCI DECADE Learning Community - Invited Workshop Leader Created and Lead Workshop on Facing Impostor Phenomena	2018
Reclaiming STEM Science Communication Workshop - Invited Speaker Presented "Building Your Social Media Brand"	2018
UCI Physics & Astronomy Stride! Peer Mentoring Mentoring & Activities Focused on Graduate Applications & Transition	2018
UCSC Osterbrock Sierra Conference Planning Comittee, Co-I Lead Professional Development Planning & Execution	2017

SPS CSULB Chapter Secretary 2013-2015

• Assist in outreach program & event planning & execution

• Assist in chapter and physics department event planning and execution

CSULB Science Outreach 2013 - 2014

Workshop Leader for Mexican American Engineers & Scientists CSULB Chapter

Past Contributed Presentations

Keck Science Meeting, Oral Presentation	September 2022
Cal-Bridge's Science by Diverse Scientists, Oral Presentation	September 2020
GalFRESCA @ UCI, Oral Presentation	August 2019
Keck Science Meeting, Poster Presentation	September 2018
UCSC Galaxy Workshop, Oral Presentation, Recording of the presentation can be found here!	August 2018
GalFRESCA, CalTech, Oral Presentation	August 2017
UCI Summer Research Symposium, Poster Presentation	August 2016
227 th AAS Meeting, Poster Presentation	January 2016
APS Far West Meeting, Oral Presentation	October 2015
CAMPARE Research Symposium, Oral Presentation	September 2015
UCI Summer Research Symposium, Oral Presentation	September 2015
CSULB Student Research Symposium, Poster Presentation	October 2014
Astrobiology Science Conference, Oral Presentation	June 2015
CAMPARE Research Symposium, Oral Presentation	September 2014
SETI Institute REU Symposium , Oral Presentation, <i>Lightening Talk</i> version found here at 22:00 minutes	August 2014
CSULB Student Research Symposium, Poster Presentation	October 2013
Conference for Undergraduate Women in Physics, Poster Presentation	January 2013
University of Texas, Brownsville REU Symposium, Oral Presentation	January 2013

Past Media Pieces_

Astronomy on Tap! March 2021

AoT Davis AoT West LA

Co-Presenter: Katy Rodriguez Wimberly

Katy Rodriguez Wimberly Receives Latino Excellence and Achievement Award

UC Irvine School of Physical Sciences News

Author: Lucas Van Wyk Joel

May 2020

PACE Yourself April 2020

UC Irvine School of Physical Sciences Features

Author: Lucas Van Wyk Joel

M. Katy Rodriguez Wimberly Profile

May 2020

1 Million Women in STEM

Author: Katy Rodriguez Wimberly

The Cal-Bridge Program

Summer 2020

Cultivating Excelencia Podcast Interview

Producer: Michelle Espino Lira

DECEMBER 20, 2022 RODRIGUEZ WIMBERLY CV 6/7

Astronomouse Winter 2019

American Physical Society Forum on Graduate Student Affairs Newsletter Author: Katy Rodriguez Wimberly

Interview with Katy Rodriguez Wimberly

Exploring New Worlds: An Astrophysicist's Journey from Academia to Industry Interviewer: Ines Juvan-Beaulieu

September 2019

Reclaiming STEM: addressing the gap in diverse and inclusive trainings June 2019

Authors: Evelyn Valdez-Ward AND Linh Sister STEM

Anh Cat

Student Spotlight: Katy Rodriguez Wimberly April 2019

UCI Physics & Astronomy Blog

California Program Cultivates Minority Physics and Astronomy Ph.D. Students October 2018

Diverse Issues in Higher Education

Cal-Bridge: Changing the Face of STEM One Student At A Time May 2018

STEM For All Multiplex

Great Gram!

Peer Pressure Ep 38: Astronomy, Not Astrology with Katy Wimberly February 2018

Interviewers: Dominic Lozano and Peer Pressure Podcast

Brandon Ongsy

November 2017 Careers with STEM Interviewer: Eliza Brockwell

Hundreds gather at UCI to witness 'Great American Eclipse' August 2017

OC Register Author: Tomoya Shimura

Student Highlight: Katy Rodriguez Wimberly April 2016

Astronomy in Color Interviewer: Jorge Moreno

CSU LSAMP PROUD - Program Recognizing Outstanding Undergraduate Distinction October 2015

California State University Louis Stokes Alliance For Minority Participation